Finding Aid for William A. Comstock Papers 1899-1949
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
William A. Comstock Papers 1899-1949
Comstock, William Alfred, 1877-1949.
Alpena, Michigan, businessman, University of Michigan regent and Democratic governor of Michigan, 1933-1934; correspondence, diaries, business papers, and other items, concerning Democratic party affairs, state and national elections, real estate and financial transactions, and photographs.
85995 Aa 2, Ac, UAm
14 linear feet
2 oversize folders
Bentley Historica Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mr. and Mrs. William A. Comstock (donor no. 991 ) and came to the library in 1940-1941. Additional materials were received in 1953.
The collection is open for research.
William A. Comstock was born in Alpena, Michigan on July 2, 1877. His father and grandfather before him were successful businessmen and Comstock would follow in this tradition. Before election to governor in 1932, Comstock was heavily involved in various businesses and investment ventures. These included the business of electric or interurban railroad construction, banking, Detroit real estate, the sugar beet industry, and oil and gas investment and development. Comstock also had a sense of public service who first sought local political office, bankrolled his political party when they were most in need of support, and offered himself as a Democratic candidate for governor at a time when the state was overwhelmingly Republican.
Comstock entered the political arena in his hometown of Alpena serving as alderman (1912-1913) and mayor (1914-1915). During this same period, Governor Woodbridge Ferris appointed Comstock to serve as regent of the University of Michigan (1913-1914). He was a loyal U-M alumnus but failed of re-election.
During the 1920s, Comstock spent much of his personal fortune trying to rebuild the state Democratic Party. He served as Democratic state chairman from 1920 to 1924 and was a member of the Democratic National Committee from 1924 to 1928. Comstock was also instrumental in the successful campaign of Woodbridge Ferris for the United States Senate. What with the money spent on political activities and economic reverses suffered near the end of the decade, Comstock by the time he came to the governor's chair was financially broke.
After three unsuccessful campaigns in 1926, 1928, and 1930, Comstock was elected governor in 1932, coming in on the Roosevelt landslide. His administration is remembered for an eight-day bank holiday that he declared well in advance of the national holiday. During his administration, the legislature passed and Comstock signed Michigan's first sales tax law - legislation which some believe was responsible for Comstock's failure to be renominated by his party in 1934.
Some of Comstock's other accomplishments while governor were emergency banking legislation to re-establish financial soundness, moratoriums on real estate mortgages and land contracts, payments of delinquent taxes on a deferred basis, and creation of a trust commission to assist in orderly liquidation and refunding of bonds issues.
Politically, Comstock was independent in his political views. Although he had been elected as part of the Roosevelt landslide, he broke ranks with the national Democratic Party and with some of the New Deal legislation. Comstock believed that Roosevelt had abandoned fundamental Democratic principles of state's rights and governmental economy. So strong was his belief that in 1940 Comstock shifted parties and supported Wendell Willkie for president. After his term as governor, Comstock held other positions of public trust. He was a member of the Michigan Civil Service Commission from 1939 to 1940; and in 1942, he was elected to the Detroit City Council where he served until his death on June 16, 1949.
The William A. Comstock papers document activities of a businessman/promoter and a Democratic Party functionary. Although the collection dates from 1902 to 1949, the bulk of the papers date from 1919 to 1932, the period of Comstock's primary business involvements. The collection has been arranged into five series: Correspondence, Other Papers and Records, Business Record Books, Diaries, and Photographs.
Subjects:
Alpena (Mich.); Alpena County (Mich.); Comstock, William Alfred, 1877-1949.; Democratic Party (Mich.); Elections--Michigan--1928.; Governors--Michigan.; Michigan. Civil Service Commission.; Michigan. Governor (1933-1934: Comstock); Michigan. Liquor Control Commission.; Michigan--Politics and government--1917-1921.; Michigan--Politics and government--1922-1928.; Michigan--Politics and government--1929-1938.; Presidents--United States--Election--1928.; Prohibition--Michigan.; Real estate business--Michigan.; United States--Politics and government--1913-1921.; United States--Politics and government--1923-1929.; United States--Politics and government--1921-1923.; United States--Politics and government--1933-1945.; United States--Politics and government--1929-1933.; University of Michigan. Board of Regents.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Alpena (Mich.)--Brewing industry.; Alpena (Mich.)--Business enterprises.; Alpena (Mich.)--Lumber industry.; Beck Brewery (Alpena, Mich.); Brewing industry--Michigan--Alpena.; Business enterprises--Michigan--Alpena.; Capitols--Michigan--Lansing.; Comstock, William Alfred, 1877-1949.; Comstock Brothers Lumber Mill.; Fishing.; Governors--Michigan.; Hospitals--Michigan.; Lansing (Mich.)--Capitols.; Lumber industry--Michigan--Alpena.; Prison facilities.; Street-railroads--Ohio.; Street-railroads--Wisconsin.; Universities and colleges--Michigan.; University of Michigan--Football.; Zeta Psi Fraternity. Xi Chapter (University of Michigan)
Contributors:
Holsaple, R. N.; Jones, Jesse H. (Jesse Holman), 1874-1956.; Miller, Sidney Trowbridge, 1864-1940.; New, Harry S. (Harry Stewart), 1858-1937.; Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), b. 1860.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Smith, Alfred Emanuel, 1873-1944.
Genre/Form:
Cyanotypes.; Diaries.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Correspondence 1908-1949, 1920-1929
  The largest series in the collection is the Correspondence which dates from 1908 to 1949 with most of the files falling in the period of the 1920s when Comstock was active in business and in the affairs of the state Democratic Party. Correspondence for the period when he was governor and after are slight. The series, although labeled as Correspondence, also includes a mixture of other types of business and legal documentation. The correspondence is of most importance for its documentation of Comstock as a successful man of business.
  - 1908-1909 (Box 1)
  - 1914-1921, 36 folders (Box 1)
  - 1922-1923, 34 folders (Box 2)
  - 1924-March 1925, 23 folders (Box 3)
  - April 1925-May 1926, 28 folders (Box 4)
  - June 1926-July 1927, 29 folders (Box 5)
  - August 1927-April 1928, 27 folders (Box 6)
  - May 1928-November 1928, 23 folders (Box 7)
  - December 1928-1929, 27 folders (Box 8)
  - January 1930-September 1930, 19 folders (Box 9)
  - October 1930-June 1931, 19 folders (Box 10)
  - July 1931-1949, 27 folders (Box 11)
- Other Papers and Records
  Other Papers and Records series is an accumulation of filed materials relating to business and politics. Included are files of Comstock as a member of the Michigan Civil Service Commission. There is also a report and an audit issued from the period when he was governor and a scrapbook and a few clippings. There is but one folder of campaign material.
  - Business agreements and real estate affairs, 5 folders (Box 12)
  - Citations, commissions, blueprints, and political banner (Box 12)
    (located in oversize folder Ac)
  - Clippings
    - General (Box 12)
    - Detroit-Windsor Tunnel Scrapbook 1927 (Box 12)
    - Campaign and gubernatorial administration (scrapbook) (Box 12)
  - Diary of trip west by Henry A. Haigh to examine mining properties for possible purchase, 1901 (Box 12)
    (Haigh was accompanied by W. B. Comstock and his son William A. Comstock)
  - Michigan Civil Service Commission materials 1939-1940, 5 folders (Box 12)
  - Michigan Liquor Control Commission, Report on Audit, December 16, 1933 to November 20, 1934 1934 (Box 12)
  - Natural Gas: report of the Michigan Public Utilities Commission Engineering Department entitled "The Market for and Supply of Natural Gas in Michigan," October 25, 1934 (Box 12)
  - Politics and campaign issues (Box 12)
  - Tax returns and tax matters, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Various topics, 5 folders (Box 12)
- Business Record Books
  Business Record Books includes corporate minute books of Comstock business interests and financial ledgers of the Democratic Party in the 1920s when Comstock was head of the state party.
  - Comstock Farm-Green and Wilson Townships (Alpena County) Journal 1907-1908 (Box 13)
  - Democratic Party cash book 1924-October 1928 (Box 13)
  - Democratic Party ledger 1924-October 1928 (Box 13)
  - Comstock-Haigh-Walker Co. record book April 1902-1919 (Box 13)
  - LaSalle Building Co. trustees record book December 1922-January 1932 (Box 13)
  - Comstock Land Co. corporate record book October 1928-February 1929 (Box 13)
  - Griswold Building Co. record book September 1927-January 1932 (Box 13)
- Diaries
  The Diaries were written in the period after his graduation from the University of Michigan when Comstock was employed as secretary of the Rochester and Eastern Rapid Railway Company. The diaries were written before Comstock became politically active and relate mainly to business matters and daily occurrences.
  - 1902-1912, 1916, 12 volumes (Box 14)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series consists of portraits of Comstock, views of Comstock with associates, scenes of fishing, a bullfight, interurbans in Wisconsin and Ohio, a University of Michigan football game and Zeta Psi house decorated for the game, the Comstock Brothers lumber mill, and various Michigan state institutions.
  - Portraits (Box 14)
    (see also oversize folder UAm)
  - WAC with others (Box 14)
  - Beck Brewery (Alpena, Mich.) (Box 14)
  - Bullfight (Mexico, 1902) (Box 14)
  - Comstock Bros. Lumber Camp and Mill (Alpena, Mich. area) (Box 14)
  - Fishing (Box 14)
  - Fremont, Ohio, 1 folders; 1 volumes (Box 14)
  - Interurbans (Wisconsin) (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 14)
  - University of Michigan football game and Zeta Psi House 1890s (Box 14)
  - "Michigan from the Air; Michigan State Institutions," prepared by the Abrams Aerial Survey circa 1931-1932 (Box 14)
Selective list of correspondents
Holsaple, R. N.
March 8, 1928
Jones, Ezra H.
April 21, 1921
Jones, Jesse Holman, 1874-1956.
February 19 and 24, 1928
Miller, Sidney Trowbridge, 1864-1940.
July 8, 1921 and January 15, 1930
New, Harry Stewart, 1858-1937.
July 8, 1921, 1923, January 15, 1930
Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), b. 1860.
February 11, 1922
Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.
October 15 and November 6, 1928, December 26, 1930
Smith, Alfred Emanuel, 1873-1944.
April 6 and 8, 1928, October 16, 1940